welcome back to APUSH and under 3
minutes no time for intros let's get
into it topic 4.9 talks about the
development of a new American culture
between 1800 and 1848 America wasn't
just growing politically or economically
it was developing its own national
identity this new National culture
combined American European and Regional
influences in art you had movements like
the Hudson River School which painted
breathtaking Landscapes of the American
frontier it wasn't just for art sake it
symbolized Manifest Destiny and the idea
that American Natural Beauty was
something special meanwhile writers like
Washington Irving gave us stories like
The Legend of Sleepy Hollow blending
European storytelling Traditions with
American settings and themes but it
wasn't all spooky stories and pretty
paintings philosophy was evolving too
case in point transcendentalism a
movement led by people like Ralph Waldo
Emerson and Henry David thorough they
believed in individualism nature and the
idea that humans could Achieve Personal
Perfection sounds inspiring right but it
also had a political Edge
transcendentalists were big on social
reform especially abolitionism and
women's right on the darker side of
American culture Gothic literature was
making its Mark the big person here is
Edgar Allan Poe with stories like The
Telltale Heart which is literally a
story describing in Vivid detail killing
an old man dismembering the body in a
bathtub and stuffing the body parts
under a floorboard I mean hats off to
this man finally architecture played a
key role in shaping the national
identity buildings in Washington DC like
the White House of the capital were
designed with neoclassical architecture
inspired by ancient Greece and Rome this
is because America wanted to position
itself as a modern Republic public with
deep roots and democratic ideals on the
screen now are AP style questions for
this topic pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now I will see you in the next one